A Guide to the Douglas Southall Freeman Papers 1900-1955
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Douglas Southall Freeman Papers 1900-1955
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5220
This collection consists of ca. 9000 items.
These papers were accumulated while Dr. Freeman was editor of the Richmond News Leader. The collection is the residue of twenty-one file drawers of material which had been purged by Freeman himself, by his secretary at his retirement, and which were reduced further for use in the current editorial work of the newspaper before the files were donated to this Library.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the Library by the Richmond News Leader on 15 November 1955.
Biographical/Historical Information
Douglas Southall Freeman was born in Lynchburg, Virginia, on May 16, 1886. He graduated from the University of Richmond with the degree of A.B. and received his Ph.D. in history from the Johns Hopkins University in 1908. He was editor of the Richmond News Leader from 1915 to 1949. Dr. Freeman pursued his interest in history in the writing of several books, among them: Lee's Lieutenants; R.E. Lee, A Biography; and George Washington. He was awarded the Pulitzer Prize for the latter two. In addition to his duties on the News Leader he became one of radio's first analysts in 1925. He commuted weekly by air to New York City to teach journalism at Columbia University (1934-1941), and was a lecturer at the Army War College for seven years. On his retirement on June 25, 1949, an article in the News Leader stated: "Dr. Freeman's editorial specialties were taxation, municipal government, military development and operations, and observations of nature." After his death on June 13, 1953 his obituary in the News Leader included the following: "He must have written close to 600,000 words a year, campaigned for the Federal Reserve Act, for abolition of the old City Administration Board, for repeal of the fee system, for establishment of the battlefield parks, for Richmond's new charter...Among the legacies he left to us here on the paper were his 'Seventy Rules for Good Writing'...he put brevity just behind accuracy in his list of virtues."
Scope and Content Information
The Douglas Southall Freeman collection comprises Freeman's editorial research files from his career as editor of the Richmond News Leader. The bulk of this material dates from 1900-1955 with several original items dated between 1819 and 1882. Transcripts of nineteenth-century material are also included. Approximately one-fifth of the foldres include material originating after Dr. Freeman's retirement. It appears that additions were made to these files under the direction of James J. Kilpatrick, Dr. Freeman's successor.
Because Dr. Freeman was a journalist and a historian, his source material includes a large numer of subjects covering a broad range of historical and current interests, which interests included taxation and finances, Civil War history, World Wars I and II, and municipal government. The collection includes circular letters, clippings, correspondence, United States government documents, memoranda, newsletters, newspapers, pamphlets, press releases, reports, and speeches. Distributed throughout the collection are some of Dr. Freeman's notes, typed manuscripts, and letters.
Many of the folders are headed with the names of people and contain either information about these people or their letters or articles. The people mentioned include local, national, or international figures cocerned with military, politics, law, science, education and industry. These folders cover such topics as the alleged treason of Jefferson Davis and Dr. Freeman's retirement, and contain such varied items as a letter written by John S. Mosby in 1902, an address by Alexander Stephens before the General Assembly of Georgia in 1866, a sketch of J.E.B. Stuart by Dr. Freeman, and James Branch Cabell's typescript essay on Thackeray's "Colonel Esmond." Under "Schiebert, Major I" can be found a manuscript entitled "Sherman's March Through Georgia," dictated by Schiebert in collaboration with Lieutenant Colonel Charles S. Venable, aide-de-camp to General Robert E. Lee. Filed under "Lee, R.E.; Farewell Order No. 9" is a letter which encloses photostatic copies of several documents related to General Lee's surrender and an article: "Manuscripts of Lee's Farewell to His Army, General Order No. 9." Several folders contain biographies most of which were supplied by the British Information Services during World War II and concern British subjects and military personnel.
Folders not headed wtih the names of people are concerned with topics such as foreign countries, finances, city government, wars, peace, and women in public affairs. The Commonwealth of Virginia and the City of Richmond receive a great deal of attention under such headings as "Civic Survey," which contains letters from the Civil Association of Richmond, of which Dr. Freeman was a member. Files on foreign countries contain information about World Wars I and II in the respective areas or wartime press releases from those countries. Other war-related materials include typed transcripts of Civil War soldiers' diaries under "Confederate Material and Federal Diary"; letters from World War II servicemen and a Confederate soldier under "War Letters"; and other materials related to World Wars I and II which are covered under headings beginning "War...", and such specific headings as "William Allen White Committee," under which is filed material on the Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies. Several folders are concerned with peace conferences, terms, and treaties, including one labeled, "Peace, the Defeat of," which contains sixty of Freeman's editorials on the subject.
Financial information may be found under headings concerning budgets, finances, taxes, and tariffs, and materials in these folders treat of the fiscal problems of cities, states, and the federal government, and include a detailed series of Freeman's editorials on tariffs and budgets. Files relating to women contain materials on women of note in early Virginia, including Pocahontas, and on the contributions of women to the United States as a whole. There is a series of fity editorials from the Richmond News Leader concerning the "Berlin Crisis" in 1948. Under "Williamsburg, Virginia" a letter from Colonial Williamsburg, Incorporated, claims for that city the erection in 1716 of America's first theater. A folder headed "War Chronology" was found to be empty and was destroyed.
Organization
All folders are filed according to their original arrangement, alphabetically by topic, and Dr. Freeman's folder hearings have been retained. A few folders were found to be out of order and were refiled. There are some apparent inconsistencies in the filing entries. For example one may find subject matter concerning taxation filed under: "Cities, Taxation" and under "Taxation, States." Within the folders items are filed in forward chronological order. Charts and maps listed at the end of this guide are filed in an oversize folder.
Contents List
- Absent Voters' Law 1943, 1950, n.d. (Box 1)
- Accidents 1936 Jul - 1951 Mar 1 (Box 1)
- Acheson, Dean 1950 Nov 30 - 1952 Oct 7 (Box 1)
- Administrative Reorganization, letter from American Bar Association 1941 Dec 11 (Box 1)
- Ages of Va. Executives 1951 Mar 29 (Box 1)
- Agriculture 1921-1951 (Box 1)
- Agricultural Adjustment Act 1935 Apr 3 - 1936 Jan 7 (Box 1)
- Air Raid Precautions 1941 Oct 8 - Dec 29 (Box 1)
- Airport, Richmond 1943 Oct 13 (Box 1)
- Alcoholism ca. 1940 (Box 1)
- Allen, George E. 1932, 1934 (Box 1)
  re depression era bank failures
- Almanacs 1931 Jan (Box 1)
- Ambler, Gordon B. ca. 1937 May (Box 1)
  congressional election platform
- America First Committee 1941 (Box 1)
- American Bank and Trust Co. 1933 Jun 2 - 1936 Jun 18 (Box 1)
- American Legion 1925 Apr 29 (Box 1)
- American Liberty League 1934 Sep 4 (Box 1)
- Anderson, Col. Henry W. 1921 Sep 27 - 1925 Oct 3 (Box 1)
- Anderson, J.A. (P.W.A.) 1935 Jun 7 - Jul 3 (Box 1)
- Annexation, Richmond 1939, 1952 (Box 1)
- A.P.V.A. Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities 1920 Feb 4 - 1940 Sep 20 (Box 1)
- Argentina 1955 Jun 16 - Sep 1 (Box 1)
- Armament 1931, 1938 (Box 1)
- Armed Service Forces (Reserve) 1955 Aug 10 - Aug 14 (Box 1)
- Arms Traffic 1925, 1933 (Box 1)
- Army, U.S. ca. 1917 - 1945 Nov. (Box 1)
- Arnold Marter (Arnold's Picket Line) 1924 Jul (Box 1)
- Artillery ca. 1916-1917 (Box 1)
- Associated Press 1932 May 23 (Box 1)
- Astor, Lady n.d. (Box 1)
- Astronomy 1946 Dec (Box 1)
- Australia 1931 May 4 - 1942 May 25 (Box 1)
- Austria 1942 Jul 24 - 1955 Sep 15 (Box 1)
- Automobile Accidents 1921 Feb 14 - 1951 Aug 3 (Box 1)
- Automobile Insurance 1931 Apr (Box 1)
- Automobiles 1901 Oct 24 - 1952 Jul (Box 1)
- Aviation 1917 Mar 11 - 1952 Feb 12 (Box 1)
- Aviation, Commercial 1928 Oct (Box 1)
- Baker, Newton D. 1918 Jan 29 - 1932 Mar 19 (Box 1)
- Ball Resolution (Forming United Nations Organization) 1943 Mar 16 (Box 1)
- Banking 1933 Jul 17 - 1953 Jun 4 (Box 1)
- Banks 1919 Jun - 1942 Feb 20 (Box 1)
- Baptists 1943 (Box 1)
- Bar 1933, 1938 (Box 1)
- Barter 1933 (Box 1)
- Battlefield Parks 1934-1937 (Box 1)
- Beacons 1943 Nov (Box 2)
- Bells 1941 Feb (Box 2)
- Benes, Dr. Edward 1941 (Box 2)
- Benjamin, Judah P. 1902, 1930 (Box 2)
- Berlin Crisis -- "Eds on In NL" [Editorials on (International) News Leader] 1948, n.d. (Box 2)
- Bethany Home 1943 (Box 2)
- Better Business Bureau 1945 (Box 2)
- Bevin, Ernest 1941, 1945 (Box 2)
- Bible 1935, n.d. (Box 2)
- Bibliography 1918-1924, n.d. (Box 2)
- Billboards 1933 (Box 2)
- Biographies, "A" - "H" 1942-1948, n.d. (Box 2)
- Biographies, "I" - "Y" 1942-1947, n.d. (Box 2)
- Biography, Army [Major Generals Brees, Packer and Moesley] n.d. (Box 2)
- Birds [The Robert Ridgway Wild Life Sanctuary] n.d. (Box 2)
- Birmingham News n.d. (Box 2)
- Birth Control 1931 (Box 2)
- Blackouts 1941, 1942 (Box 2)
- Blair, Miss Lulie 1946 (Box 2)
- Blind (Blindness) 1921-1925 (Box 2)
- Blood 1943, ca. 1943 (Box 2)
- Blue Mold 1940 (Box 2)
- Boatwright, F.S. 1948 (Box 2)
- Bolshevism 1919-1920, n.d. (Box 2)
- Bonds 1932 May 26 (Box 2)
- Books 1928-1945 (Box 2)
- Booth, John Wilkes 1925 May 17 (Box 2)
- Boston, Nancy 1949-1950, n.d. (Box 2)
- Boy Scouts 1919, n.d. (Box 2)
- Bradley, Gen. Omar 1951 (Box 2)
- Bragg, Braxton 1924 (Box 2)
- Bread 1945 (Box 2)
- Breckenridge, Henry 1939 (Box 2)
- Brick, Early Colonial Virginia 1931 (Box 2)
- Bridges (Tolls) 1930-1946 (Box 2)
- Brooke-Popham, Air Marshall Sir Robert 1941 (Box 2)
- Brown, J. Sinclair ca. 1931 (Box 2)
- Bruening, Chancellor 1931 (Box 2)
- Brusiloff, Gen. Alexis A. 1917 (Box 2)
- Buckwheat cakes 1937 (Box 2)
- Budget, State, Editorials in the Richmond News Leader1931 (Box 2)
- Budget systems 1917 (Box 2)
- Buggs Island 1951 (Box 2)
- Building codes n.d. (Box 2)
- Bulganin, Premier Nikolai A. 1955 (Box 2)
- Burma 1943-1944 (Box 2)
- Burma Road 1941-1944 (Box 2)
- Buses ca. 1922-1934 (Box 2)
- Byrd Airport 1947 (Box 3)
- Byrd, Harry F. 1925 (Box 3)
- Cabell, James Branch 1937-1955 (Box 3)
- Camp Lee 1921 (Box 3)
- Camp Peary 1950 (Box 3)
- Canada 1930, 1941 (Box 3)
- Canal Boats 1930 (Box 3)
- Cancer 1946, 1951, n.d. (Box 3)
- Cannon, Bishop James 1917-1931, n.d. (Box 3)
- Carter, Dean Hall 1932 (Box 3)
- Capital Square [Gates] 1943 (Box 3)
- Capitol Va. state 1936 (Box 3)
- Capper-Kelley Bill 1928 (Box 3)
- Cardwell, W.D. 1928, n.d. (Box 3)
- Carillon 1925-1926, n.d. (Box 3)
- "Carry Me Back to Old Va." 1940 (Box 3)
- Carter, Oberlin M. 1939-1941 (Box 3)
- Catalonia n.d. (Box 3)
- Cartels 1932 (Box 3)
- Casualties 1943 (Box 3)
- Catholic Church 1926-1950 (Box 3)
- Censorship 1942-1945 (Box 3)
- Census 1932, 1936 (Box 3)
- Certificate, Douglas S. Freeman, Member of Phi Beta Kappa Associates 1940
- Certificate, Dr. Douglas Freeman, "A Member of the Virginia War History Comission" 1919
- Chain Stores 1930-1943 (Box 3)
- Chancellorsville, Battle of 1863 n.d. (Box 3)
- Charities 1941, n.d. (Box 3)
- Charter changes 1946-1949 (Box 3)
- Charts (Twelve), Distribution of funds under the Emergency Relief Appropriation Acts of 1935 and 1936 ca. 1935
- Cheese 1928 (Box 3)
- Chemistry 1930-1931 (Box 3)
- Chesapeake & Ohio R.R. 1925 (Box 3)
- Chesterfield County 1933, 1937 (Box 3)
- Chaing Kai-shek 1943-1944 (Box 3)
- Chaing Kai-shek, Mme. 1943 (Box 3)
- Child Labor 1925-1947, n.d. (Box 3)
- Children 1918-1930 (Box 3)
- China 1918-1930 (Box 3)
- China, Red 1955 (Box 3)
- Christian Front 1940 (Box 3)
- Christmas 1925-1928, n.d. (Box 3)
- Christmas Midnight Mass n.d. (Box 3)
- Christian, W.T. 1942 (Box 3)
- Chrysler Corporation 1937 (Box 3)
- Church survey 1928, n.d. (Box 3)
- Churches 1905-1948, n.d. (Box 3)
- Churchill, Winston 1942-1952 (Box 3)
- Cities 1922-1946, n.d. (Box 3)
- Cities, Financial Status 1927, 1931 (Box 4)
- Cities, Taxation 1925 (Box 4)
- City Charter Change 1906, 1917, n.d. (Box 4)
- City Farm 1921 (Box 4)
- City Manager 1921-1947, n.d. (Box 4)
- City Planning, Richmond ca. 1924-1939, n.d. (Box 4)
- City Point Railroad 1938 (Box 4)
- Civic Survey 1912-1917, n.d. (Box 4)
- Civil Liberties 1940 (Box 4)
- Civil Rights Congress (re the Martinsville Seven) 1950, 1951, n.d. (Box 4)
- Civil Rights Editorials 1951 (Box 4)
- Civil Service 1931-1948 (Box 4)
- Civilian Defense 1942 (Box 4)
- Clark, Justice Tom C. 1949 (Box 4)
- Clemenceau, Premier George 1919, 1922 (Box 4)
- Coal 1917-1950, n.d. (Box 4)
- Coal Miners 1952 (Box 4)
- Coast Guard ca. 1930 (Box 4)
- Coast Artillery School, Fort Monroe 1935 (Box 4)
- Coast and Geodetic Survey 1930 (Box 4)
- Coleman, Judge F.W. 1935 (Box 4)
- Coffin Award 1931 (Box 4)
- Colleges 1934-1945 (Box 4)
- Colleges, State Teachers ca. 1935 (Box 4)
- Colleges, Virginia 1951 (Box 4)
- Colombia 1931-1932 (Box 4)
- Columbus, C. 1925, n.d. (Box 4)
- Commerce, Foreign and Interstate 1918-1933 (Box 4)
- Communism 1938-1952 (Box 4)
- Company Unions 1937 (Box 4)
- Confederate Balloon 1944 (Box 4)
- Confederate Material and Federal Diary (Typed Transcripts) 1854-1857, 1916-1937 (Box 4)
- Confederate Women's Home 1932, 1947 (Box 4)
- Co-Graduate [U.Va.] ca. 1918, n.d. (Box 4)
- Congress 1937, 1945 (Box 4)
- Congress, 81st 1949 (Box 4)
- Congress, 82nd 1950-1953 (Box 4)
- Congressional Record 1952 (Box 4)
- Connally, Sen. Tom 1950 (Box 4)
- Conquest, Edwin 1940-1943 (Box 4)
- Conscription 1917, 1943 (Box 4)
- Constitution, U.S. (chiefly re amendments) 1926-1951 (Box 4)
- Constitutional Amendments, Va. 1928 (Box 5)
- Constitutions 1931 (Box 5)
- Contempt Case 1917 (Box 5)
- Cooke, Rev. Giles B. 1927-1930 (Box 5)
- Co-operation 1923 (Box 5)
- Cooperative Marketing 1926-1943, n.d. (Box 5)
- Copper 1923 (Box 5)
- Copyrights 1921-1928, n.d. (Box 5)
- Corporation Comission, State 1938, 1949 (Box 5)
- Cork 1942, 1943 (Box 5)
- Cost of Living 1922-1951 (Box 5)
- Costa Rica 1941 (Box 5)
- Cotton ca. 1932-1946 (Box 5)
- Cotton Mills 1926, 1930 (Box 5)
- Coughlin, Father 1938-1942 (Box 5)
- Coulbourn, William Clark n.d. (Box 5)
- Council, City ca. 1935, n.d. (Box 5)
- Counties, Virginia 1930 (Box 5)
- County Government ca. 1938-1939 (Box 5)
- Court of Appeals, Virginia 1951 (Box 5)
- Court Reporting 1952 (Box 5)
- Courts, Federal ca. 1919-1926 (Box 5)
- Crater, Battle of (Dialogue) 1937 (Box 5)
- Credit Men, Inc. 1937 (Box 5)
- Credit Unions ca. 1923-1953, n.d. (Box 5)
- Credits 1930 (Box 5)
- Crete 1941 (Box 5)
- Crime 1925-1936 (Box 5)
- Crippled Children's Hospital ca. 1950 (Box 5)
- Crop Insurance n.d. (Box 5)
- Cruelty to Animals 1932, n.d. (Box 5)
- Cuba 1930, n.d. (Box 5)
- Currency 1932-1948 (Box 5)
- Curley, James Michael 1931 (Box 5)
- Customs Inspection 1927, 1931 (Box 5)
- Cyclotrons 1940 (Box 5)
- Czech Crisis Editorials (Richmond News Leader) 1938 (Box 5)
- Chezcho-slovakia 1918-1946, n.d. (Box 5)
- Dabney, Virginius 1925 (Box 5)
- Dancy Lectures at Alabama College 1941 (Box 5)
- Davis, A.K., Jr. 1935 (Box 5)
- Davis, Jefferson 1866-1882, 1922, 1923, n.d. (Box 5)
  including ALS and typed manuscripts
- Davis, Gov. Westmoreland 1912, 1922 (Box 5)
- Dawes Plan 1925 (Box 5)
- Daylight Saving ca. 1926, n.d. (Box 5)
- Deafness 1935-1936 (Box 5)
- Death Rate, Richmond 1922 (Box 5)
- Debt, Allied 1922-1936, n.d. (Box 5)
- Debts, Cities 1941 (Box 5)
- Debts, Public 1932-1933 (Box 5)
- Decatur Herald 1953 (Box 5)
- Decorations 1941 (Box 5)
- Defense Council 1941-1942, n.d. (Box 5)
- Democratic National Convention 1952 (Box 6)
- Democratic Party, Va. 1944, 1952 (Box 6)
- DeRenne Correspondence - Confederate Permanent Constitution 1917-1918 (Box 6)
- Devaluation / Dewey, John ca. 1934, 1929, 1931 (Box 6)
- Dionne Quintuplets 1934, 1944 (Box 6)
- Diptheria ca. 1920, ca. 1924 (Box 6)
- Disarmament 1934, 1951 (Box 6)
- Disarmament Conference of 1932 1934 (Box 6)
- Disasters, Richmond (typed excerpts) 1780-1781, 1912, 1922 (Box 6)
- Doak, William N. 1931 (Box 6)
- Douglas, Paul 1951 (Box 6)
- Dooley's (Major) Will 1919-1922 (Box 6)
- Dover Association 1933 (Box 6)
- Drinard, James C. ca. 1934 (Box 6)
- Drugs 1934 (Box 6)
- Dulles, John Foster 1950-1955, n.d. (Box 6)
- Dumbarton Oaks 1944-1945 (Box 6)
- Dutch Elm Disease n.d. (Box 6)
- Dyer Anti-Lynching Bill 1928 (Box 6)
- Earthquakes 1946 (Box 6)
- Education ca. 1915 - ca. 1950, n.d. (Box 6)
- Education, Negro 1944 (Box 6)
- Education, Va. 1951-1953, n.d. (Box 6)
- Employees, Richmond 1950, n.d. (Box 6)
- Employment Bureau 1939 (Box 6)
- Equal Rights 1943 (Box 6)
- Espionage 1939, 1942 (Box 6)
- Euthanasis / Evolution 1940, 1925, n.d. (Box 6)
- Excess Profits Tax 1940 (Box 6)
- Express Highway 1950, 1951, n.d. (Box 6)
- Farm Demonstration 1939 (Box 6)
- Farm, State (A Virginia Correctional Institutional) 1941 (Box 6)
- Fascism 1941 (Box 6)
- Federal Reserve 1916-1930, n.d. (Box 6)
- Fields, B.A. ca. 1953 (Box 6)
- Fight for Freedom Committee ca. 1940 (Box 6)
- Finances, Federal 1951-ca. 1954 (Box 6)
- Finances, General, London "Economist" 1941 (Box 6)
- Finances, Richmond ca. 1916-1948, n.d. (Box 6)
- Finances, State 1954 (Box 6)
- Finances, United States 1919-1953, n.d. (Box 6)
- Finances, Virginia 1930-1952 (Box 7)
- Finland ca. 1929 - 1941 (Box 7)
- Fires 1941-ca. 1950 (Box 7)
- First Virginia Regiment 1924-1934, n.d. (Box 7)
- Fisheries 1949 (Box 7)
- Flags 1922-1936, n.d. (Box 7)
- Floods 1937 (Box 7)
- Foch, Marshal 1917, 1921 (Box 7)
- Folklore, Virginia 1919 (Box 7)
- Foods 1938, n.d. (Box 7)
- Football 1940-1951 (Box 7)
- Ford, Henry 1925-1931 (Box 7)
- Foreign Ministeries Conference 1951 (Box 7)
- Foreign Trade 1917-1934 (Box 7)
- Foreign Exchange 1932 (Box 7)
- Foreign Policy 1940, 1950 (Box 7)
- Forestry 1925-1937, n.d. (Box 7)
- Forests, National 1952 (Box 7)
- Formosa 1950-1951 (Box 7)
- Fort Harrison 1934, n.d. (Box 7)
- Forty Hour Week 1942 (Box 7)
- France ca. 1914-1955, n.d. (Box 7)
- Frankfurter, Felix 1934 (Box 7)
- Franking ca. 1941 (Box 7)
- Fred, Edwin Broun 1947-1948 (Box 7)
- Fredericksburg, Va. 1925 (Box 7)
- Freedom ca. 1919-1941 (Box 7)
- Freeman, D.S. 1949 (Box 7)
- Freight Rates 1943 (Box 7)
- Fulbright, Wm. J. 1951 (Box 7)
- Gaitskell, Hugh 1950 (Box 7)
- Gallup Poll 1941 (Box 7)
- Gambling 1935-ca. 1951 (Box 7)
- Game and Inland Fisheries Department 1939, 1950 (Box 7)
- Gardens 1942 (Box 7)
- Garnett, W.E. ca. 1941 (Box 7)
- Gas, City 1949, 1950, n.d. (Box 7)
- Gas, Natural 1950 (Box 7)
- Gasoline 1933-1941 (Box 7)
- Gasoline Tax 1947, 1950 (Box 7)
- Garton, Chief O.D. 1950 (Box 7)
- Genealogy (Bell Family, Mrs. Chambers) 1947, n.d. (Box 7)
- Geography n.d. (Box 7)
- George VI, King 1937 (Box 7)
- Georgia 1921-1941 (Box 7)
- Germany 1918-1955, n.d. (Box 7)
- Gibraltar 1937, ca. 1940 (Box 7)
- Girl Scouts 1937 (Box 7)
- Glasgow, Arthur 1942, n.d. (Box 7)
- Glass n.d. (Box 7)
- Glass, Carter 1927-1944 (Box 7)
- Gold 1933-1952 (Box 7)
- Gorman, Mary n.d. (Box 7)
- Goto, Fumio ca. 1932 (Box 7)
- Government, Cost of 1932 (Box 7)
- Grade Crossings 1944 (Box 7)
- Graham, F.P. 1942 (Box 7)
- Grand National 1928 (Box 7)
- The Grand Rapids Herald 1953 (Box 7)
- Great Britain 1923-1955, n.d. (Box 7)
- Greece 1940-1944 (Box 8)
- Guard Rails 1934 (Box 8)
- Gubernatorial Campaign of 1945 1945 (Box 8)
- Guggenheim Memorial Foundation ca. 1925-1941 (Box 8)
- Gunn, Judge Julien 1935 (Box 8)
- Hampden-Sydney 1924-1944 (Box 8)
- Hampton Roads 1930-1942, n.d. (Box 8)
- Henson, Mathew 1934 (Box 8)
- Harmon, Frances S. 1934 (Box 8)
- Harvard University 1906, 1936, n.d. (Box 8)
- Hatch Bill 1940 (Box 8)
- Hawaii 1955, n.d. (Box 8)
- Hayes, Jr., Mr. J. 1929 (Box 8)
- Heating 1943 (Box 8)
- Helicopters 1954 (Box 8)
- Henry, Patrick (from William Wirt Henry) n.d. (Box 8)
- Hepburn, David 1922-1928 (Box 8)
- Herriot, E. 1932 (Box 8)
- Highway Commission ca. 1939 (Box 8)
- High Schools 1939 (Box 8)
- Highways 1939-1952 (Box 8)
- Hiss, Alger 1949 (Box 8)
- Historic Places, Richmond 1930, n.d. (Box 8)
- Historical Supplement, News Leader 1924-1925 (Box 8)
- History 1943 (Box 8)
- Hollywood Cemetary 1941 (Box 8)
- Hitler, A. 1939-1943 (Box 8)
- Holmes, Justice Oliver Wendell 1931 (Box 8)
- Homicides 1933 (Box 8)
- Hong Kong 1941 (Box 8)
- Hoover, Herbert 1920-1954 (Box 8)
- Hopewell 1922-1940 (Box 8)
- Hopkins, Arthur (excerpts from Cue) 1935 (Box 8)
- Hopkins, Ernest 1940 (Box 8)
- Horses 1933-1942 (Box 8)
- Hospitals 1926-1952 (Box 8)
- Hospitals, Richmond (Latimer Articles) 1952 Jan (Box 8)
- Housing 1919-1949, n.d. (Box 8)
- Housing, Richmond ca. 1919-1950, n.d. (Box 8)
- Howell, Thos. B. ca. 1933 (Box 8)
- Hubard, William James (transcripts) 1859-1860, n.d. (Box 8)
- Hungary 1924-1951 (Box 8)
- Hutchins, Robert 1937 (Box 8)
- Hutchinson, Martin A. 1946 (Box 8)
- India ca. 1928-1942, n.d. (Box 8)
- Indians 1924-1932 (Box 8)
- Ickes, Harold 1940 (Box 8)
- Immigration ca. 1924-1952 (Box 8)
- Incomes ca. 1928-1951 (Box 8)
- Income Tax 1926-1951, n.d. (Box 8)
- Income Tax, Virginia ca. 1935 (Box 8)
- Incunabula 1930 (Box 8)
- Industrial Conditions 1932, 1942 (Box 8)
- Industries, Virginia ca. 1929 (Box 8)
- Infantile Paralysis 1944-1953 (Box 8)
- Injunctions 1931 (Box 9)
- Inland Waterways 1931, 1933 (Box 9)
- Insanity 1936, 1943 (Box 9)
- Insignia (Armed Forces, U.S. and U.K.) ca. 1944, n.d. (Box 9)
- Installment Buying 1943 (Box 9)
- Insurance 1931-1952 (Box 9)
- Insurance, Auto 1951 (Box 9)
- Insurance, Fire 1939-1943 (Box 9)
- Insurance, Liability 1938 (Box 9)
- Internal Security 1951 (Box 9)
- Interracial Commission 1935 (Box 9)
- Investments 1935 (Box 9)
- Iran 1945 (Box 9)
- Ireland and Irish 1926-1951 (Box 9)
- Italy 1943 (Box 9)
- Jackson, Stonewall (Transcripts) 1863, 1932 (Box 9)
- Jails n.d. (Box 9)
- Jails n.d. (Box 9)
- James, Father J.R. 1940 (Box 9)
- James River 1923-1944 (Box 9)
- Japan 1919-1950, n.d. (Box 9)
- Japan, Peace Treaty 1951 (Box 9)
- Japanese 1943 (Box 9)
- Japanese Beetles 1941 (Box 9)
- Jasper, Rev. John 1935 (Box 9)
- Jefferson, Thomas 1936-1944, n.d. (Box 9)
- Jessup, Philip C. 1951 (Box 9)
- Jordan, Police Chief 1926 (Box 9)
- Juvenile Court ca. 1946, 1949, n.d. (Box 9)
- Juvenile Delinquency ca. 1933 (Box 9)
- Kagawa, Toyohiko 1931, 1945 (Box 9)
- Kefauver Crime Report 1951 (Box 9)
- Kellam Case 1953 (Box 9)
- Kellogg Briand Treaty 1932 (Box 9)
- Korea 1950-1952, n.d. (Box 9)
- Ku Klux Klan 1919-1942, n.d. (Box 9)
- Krivitsky, Walter G. 1941 (Box 9)
- Labor 1931-1951 (Box 9)
- Labor, Virginia 1946, 1953, n.d. (Box 9)
- Labor Department, Virginia 1941 (Box 9)
- Lame Duck Amendment 1933 (Box 9)
- Lawrence, William L. 1945 (Box 9)
- Layton, Sir Geoffrey 1941 (Box 9)
- Lamar, Mrs. W.D. 1935 (Box 9)
- Lattimore, Owen J. 1950, 1952 (Box 9)
- League of Nations 1919-1920 (Box 9)
- Lease Lend Act 1943-1944 (Box 9)
- Lee, Fitzhugh (with Typed Transcript) 1915, 1928, n.d. (Box 9)